<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by lcollins (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- Sid Meier's Civilization 4 -->
<!-- Copyright Firaxis Games 2005 -->
<!-- -->
<!-- Game Text - New -->
<Civ4GameText xmlns="http://www.firaxis.com">
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_BARTON_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Edmund Barton[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]First Prime Minister of Australia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]18 January, 1849 - 7 January, 1920[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Sir Edmund Barton, Australian politician and judge, was the first Prime Minister of Australia and a founding justice of the High Court of Australia.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Barton's greatest contribution to Australian history was his management of the federation movement through the 1890s. Elected at the inaugural 1901 federal election, Barton resigned from the position of Prime Minister of Australia in 1903 and became a judge of Australia's High Court.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_LALOR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Peter Lalor[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Leader of the Eureka Stockade rebellion[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]5 February 1827 - 9 February 1889[PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Peter was born in the family home of Tinakill, at Raheen County Laois, (then known as Queen's County), Ireland, the son of Patrick Lalor, a landowner and supporter of the abolition of tithes who held a seat in the House of Commons from 1832 to 1835 as the first Catholic MP for Queens County Ireland since the reign of James II. His mother was Anne Dillon, they had 11 sons of which Peter Fintan Lalor was one. His mother died 4 June 1835 and his father remarried Ellen Mary Anne Loughnan, no children. Patrick Lalor, MP born circa 1781 died 10 April 1856.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Lalor was educated at Carlton College then trained as a civil engineer at Trinity College, Dublin. He became a leader of the Irish Confederation and the 'Young Ireland' movement of 1848.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][NEWLINE]With his brother Richard, Lalor emigrated to Australia in October 1852, arriving in the district during November 1852 he worked on the construction of the Melbourne-Geelong railway line but before long joined the Victorian Gold Rush and began mining in the Ovens Valley, and then to Eureka Lead at Ballarat.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Lalor led the miners' opposition to the incompetent and often brutal administration of the goldfields, and was elected to lead the men of the stockade, in which he was wounded and, ultimately, had his arm amputated. A warrant for Lalor's arrest for sedition was initially sought, but he was taken from Ballarat and hidden in Young Queen Hotel of South Geelong by supporters until juries had found a number of other miners involved in the stockade not guilty of sedition in May and June 1855. The warrant for his arrest was withdrawn.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Lalor was described in the reward notice issued in 1854 as being:[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][TAB]"Hair dark brown, whiskers dark brown and shaved under the chin, no moustache, long face, rather good looking, and is a well made man."[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Legislation was passed to give miners a the right to vote; a new form of licensing of Miners Rights costing £2 per year later reduced to £1. The monthly gold tax was abolished. All miners, the three of Bentley's Eureka Hotel fire and the 114 of the Eureka Stockade Ballarat were set free including Peter Lalor, now an amputee who had been in hiding at his fiancée's Geelong home.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The enormous political changes after the Eureka Stockade saw Lalor appointed to the Victorian parliament's Legislative Council in 1855. In 1856, under the new, more democratic constitution (featuring near-universal non Aboriginal, non female suffrage) Lalor was elected to the Legislative Assembly (lower house) seat of North Grenville (Ballarat West) and in 1859 he transferred to the seat of South Grant, which he was to hold for the rest of his life.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]He was postmaster-general (August to October 1875) and minister for trade and customs (May 1877 until March 1880) both positions in the ministry of Sir Graham Berry from 1877 to 1879, and chairman of committees.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]As successor to Sir Charles Gavan Duffy, his most effective political post was probably that of Speaker of the Legislative Assembly of Victoria, a post he held from 1880 until 1887 until illness forced his retirement; he was awarded a retiring pension of 4,000 pounds by parliament.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Alicia Dunne living in Geelong with her parents, her uncle was Father Patrick Dunne who was chaplain of Pentridge Mission (now known as Coburg) and was moved to Geelong in 1853, she moved with him to become a teacher at St. Mary’s School. Peter Lalor's fiancée since June 1854 they married on 10 July 1855 in Geelong. On 5 May 1855 they both returned to Ballarat to bid for land on sale. Their first child was their daughter Annie born in Prahran in 1856 and their son Joseph was born at Sandridge on 18 December 1857 (Sandridge is now Port Melbourne). Annie married Thomas Lempriere in 1882 and died in 1885 of pulmonary phthisis aged 29 years, buried in the Lalor Grave at New Melbourne Cemetery; Joseph became Dr Lalor and married Agnes McCormick of Dublin, Ireland.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_DEAKIN_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Alfred Deakin[\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Second Prime Minister of Australia[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD]3 August 1856 - 7 October 1919[PARAGRAPH:2:1][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE]Australian politician, was a leader of the movement for Australian federation and later second Prime Minister of Australia. In the last quarter of the nineteenth century, Deakin was a major contributor to the establishment of liberal reforms in the colony of Victoria, including the protection of rights at work. He also played a major part in establishing irrigation in Australia. It is likely that he could have been Premier of Victoria, but he chose to devote his energy to federation.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Throughout the 1890s Deakin was a participant in conferences of representatives of the Australian colonies that were established to draft a constitution for the proposed federation. He played an important role in ensuring that the draft was liberal and democratic and in achieving compromises to enable its eventual success. Between conferences, he worked to popularise the concept of federation and campaigned for its acceptance in colonial referenda. He then fought hard to ensure acceptance of the proposed constitution by the Government of the United Kingdom.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]As Prime Minister, Deakin completed a vast legislative program that makes him, with Labor's Andrew Fisher, the founder of an effective Commonwealth government. He expanded the High Court, provided major funding for the purchase of ships—leading to the establishment of the Royal Australian Navy as a significant force under the Fisher government—and established Australian control of Papua. Confronted by the rising Australian Labor Party in 1909, he merged his Protectionist Party with George Reid's Free Trade Party to create the Fusion, the main ancestor of the modern Liberal Party of Australia.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_KOORI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Koori (also spelled Koorie) is a word which some Indigenous Australians in New South Wales and Victoria use to identify themselves, and has become a well established term to mean 'Indigenous Australians from south eastern Australia'.[PARAGRAPH:2]Many Indigenous Australians dislike the terms 'Aborigine' and 'Aboriginal' because these terms have been forced on them. They prefer to use words from their own languages. In some languages of south-east Australia (parts of New South Wales and Victoria), the words: coorie, kory, kuri, kooli, koole mean 'person' or 'people'. In the 1960s, the form koori came to be used by Indigenous Australians of these areas to mean 'Aboriginal people' or 'Aboriginal person'.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_MURRI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Murri are the indigenous Australians that traditionally occupied most of modern-day Queensland. The term is sometimes erroneously used for populations from other parts of Australia. They are a collection of tribes and extended family groups throughout the region (such as the Yugarabul, the Jagara peoples from Coorparoo, and the Kwiambal peoples from further south). Aboriginal communities from other regions of Australia include Koori, Anangu, Noongar, Nunga.[PARAGRAPH:2]Many Murri were forcibly removed from their land, and placed on reserves with other tribes with whom their relations may not have been friendly. From 1900 until 1972, a substantial number of Murri children became part of the Stolen Generation[PARAGRAPH:2]The situation of the Murri people has improved over recent decades, they were given suffrage in 1965, along with free access to Musgrave Park; they now own and operate the Murri radio network; and Murri courts were established in 2002.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NOONGAR_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Noongar (alternate spellings: Nyungar/Nyoongar/Nyoongah/Nyungah/Nyugah), are an indigenous Australian people who live in the south-west corner of Western Australia from Geraldton on the west coast to Esperance on the south coast. Their country extends from Jurien Bay in the north to the southern coast, and east to Ravensthorpe and Southern Cross. 'Noongar' is also the name for their common language. Their name, in the various original dialects is thought to mean "people". In the south, the spelling 'Noongar' is preferred, reflecting a broader accent.[PARAGRAPH:2][H1]History[\H1][NEWLINE]Prior to the arrival of Europeans, the Noongar population has been variously estimated at between 6,000 and some tens of thousands. Colonisation by the British resulted in both violence and new diseases, taking a heavy toll on the population. Nowadays, however, according to the Noongar themselves, they number more than 28,000. The 2001 census figures showed that 21,000 people identified themselves as indigenous in the south-west of Western Australia. In 2006, the community claimed to number over 28,000 people.[PARAGRAPH:2]Traditional Noongar made a living by hunting and trapping a variety of game, including kangaroos, possums and wallabies; by fishing using spears and fish traps; as well as by gathering an extensive range of edible wild plants, including wattle seeds. Noongar people utilised quartz instead of flint for spear and knife edges and developed a now-lost art of working quartz crystals.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Noongar considered themselves of superior culture, especially in comparison with the invading British. Reflecting this attitude, they called the newcomers Djanga (or djanak), meaning "white devils". From early on, the Noongar were wary in their dealings with the Europeans, having had unfortunate contact with sealers kidnapping and marooning Aboriginal women on the south coast. The Noongar were horrified by what they perceived as the waste and slaughter whites brought to the lands that were their home. The Noongar lived in large extended family groups and, historically, their way of life included a respect and reverence for the land that fed them.[PARAGRAPH:2]Yagan arose as one of a number of leaders of the Noongar at the time when British settlers first arrived in the Swan River area in 1829 and Captain James Stirling declared that the local tribes were British subjects. Although at first the Noongar traded amicably with the settlers, rifts and misunderstandings developed as land seizures went on, and attacks and reprisal attacks soon escalated. An example of such misunderstandings was the Noongar land-management practice of setting fires in early summer, mistakenly seen as an act of hostility by the settlers. Conversely, the Noongar saw the settlers' livestock as fair game to replace the dwindling stocks of native animals shot indiscriminately by settlers. Yagan participated in a number of food raids and in killing settlers in retaliation for the deaths of Noongar at white hands - notably, he warned nearby whites repeatedly that one white life would be taken for every Noongar killed by a white. He was shot by a shepherd boy and is now considered by many to have been one of the first indigenous resistance fighters.[PARAGRAPH:2]From August 1838 ten Aboriginal prisoners were sent to Rottnest Island (known as Wadjemup to the Noongar, possibly meaning "place across the water"). After a short period when both settlers and prisoners occupied the island, the Colonial Secretary announced in June 1839 that the island would become a penal establishment for Aboriginal people and, between 1838 and 1931, Rottnest Island was used as a prison to transfer Aboriginal prisoners "overseas". In "pacifying" an Aboriginal population, men were rounded up and chained for offences ranging from spearing livestock, burning the bush or digging vegetables on what had been their own land. It has been estimated that there may be as many as 369 Aboriginal graves on the island, of which five were for prisoners who were hanged. Except for a short period between 1849 and 1855, during which the prison was closed, some 3,700 Aboriginal men and boys, many of them Noongars, but also many others from all parts of the state, were imprisoned.[PARAGRAPH:2]From 1890 to 1958, the lives and lifestyles of Noongar people were subject to the Native Welfare Act. Two state-run "concentration" camps, Moore River Native Settlement and Carrolup (later known as Marribank), became the home of up to one-third of the population. It is estimated that 10 to 25% of Noongar children were forcibly “adopted” during these years, in part of what has become known as the Stolen Generations</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_YAMATJI_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Yamatji is the name of an important Aboriginal people of the Murchison, Gascoyne and Pilbara regions of the North West of Western Australia, and comes from the word "friend" in the local languages of the area. Before contact it is questionable about the degree of self-identification of these people as Yamatji, as there were significant cultural differences between coastal dwelling groups, who generally did not practice male initiation circumcision, and the larger groups of the interior like the Walpuri of the bend in the Lyons River, who did.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Yamatji people were instrumental in assisting early settlers in the area identify permanent water sources, and worked in the pearling, pastoral and fishing industries. Especially in the early period their suffering as a result of the contact with the settler community was illustrated in 1885 by the Rev J. Gribble, who when arriving at Carnarvon found 36 men chained by the neck to a tree. His subsequent publication "Dark Deeds in a Sunny Land" portrayed the suffering of the Yamatji.[PARAGRAPH:2]From 1908 to 1918, Dore and Bernier Islands, off the coast of Carnarvon, operated as Lock Hospitals for the isolation of Aboriginal men and women supposedly suffering from venereal diseases. Often not knowing the reason for their removal, they were kept on the island until they either died or recovered.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_NUNGA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Nunga is a term of self-reference for many of the Aboriginal peoples of southern South Australia.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_ANANGU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>Anangu, more accurately "Arnangu" (pronounced mid-way between "Arn Ang Goo" and "An An Ooo", with the stress on the first syllable; is a word found in a number of eastern varieties of the Western Desert Language (WDL), an Australian Aboriginal language of the Pama-Nyungan family, spoken in the desert regions of western and central Australia. Before the arrival of non-Aboriginal people in Central Australia the core meaning of anangu was probably 'human being, person'. Now however it is used to mean 'Aboriginal human being, person' and is rarely applied to non-Aboriginal people. As a Western Desert Language word for '(Aboriginal) person', and given that other Aboriginal languages have their own words for '(Aboriginal) person' the word anangu has come to be very closely associated with the WDL speaking people who use it to the extent that it is now commonly used to refer to them, mainly by non-Aboriginal people but also by the speakers themselves. Used in this way it seems never to be used to refer to any traditional grouping but rather to any collection of WDL people. It may also be used to refer to other Aboriginal people, especially where the speaker is uncertain who they are.[PARAGRAPH:2]Anangu also has the meaning 'human body' and may be used to refer specifically to the physical body, or to a dead body.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_YOLNGU_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Yolngu are an Indigenous Australian people inhabiting north-eastern Arnhem Land in the Northern Territory of Australia. Yolngu literally means “person” in the language spoken by the people.[PARAGRAPH:2][H1]History[\H1][NEWLINE]Yolngu sustained good trade relations with Macassan fisherman for several hundred years. The Macassan respected the land as Yolngu land; they only ever camped on the beach, and generally avoided contact with Yolngu women.[PARAGRAPH:2]They made yearly visits to harvest trepang and pearls, paying Yolngu in kind with goods such as knives, metal, canoes, tobacco and pipes.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1906, the South Australian Government did not renew the Macassan's permit to harvest trepang. This loss of trade caused some disruption to the Yolngu way of life, particularly since they did not know why the Macassan had stopped coming.[PARAGRAPH:2]Yolngu had well established trade routes within Australia, extending to Central Australian clans and other Aboriginal countries. (For example, they did not make boomerangs, but obtained these via trade from Central Australia. This contact was maintained through use of message sticks, as well as mailmen – with some men walking several hundred kilometres in their work to send messages and relay orders between tribes and countries.[PARAGRAPH:3]Yolngu had known about Europeans prior to the arrival of British in Australia through their contact with Macassan traders, which probably began around the sixteenth century. Their word for European, Balanda, is derived from "Hollaender" (Dutch person).[PARAGRAPH:3]In the late nineteenth century, white Australians began to "open up" Arnhem Land for cattle grazing. A series of battles between Yolngu and Balanda occurred at this time. Yolngu were arguably more warrior-like than other Indigenous Australians because they had had to defend their northern shoreline for many hundreds – if not thousands – of years.[PARAGRAPH:2]There was also a series of massacres.[PARAGRAPH:2]Two notable cases are an instance at Florida Station, around 1885 where Yolngu were fed poisoned horsemeat after they killed and ate some cattle (under their law, Madayin, it was their land and they had an inalienable right to eat animals on their land). Many people died as a result of that incident.[PARAGRAPH:2]Another incident took place around 1895. Some Yolngu took a small amount of barbed wire from a huge roll to build fishing spears. Men, women and children were chased by mounted police and men on horseback from the Eastern and African Cold Storage Company and shot.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_CIV_PALAWAH_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>The Palawa are the indigenous people of the island state of Tasmania, Australia.[PARAGRAPH:2]During 1803-33, the population of the Tasmanian Aborigines was reduced from an estimate of around 5,000 to around 300, largely from diseases introduced by British settlers and conflict with British settlers. The last confirmed "full blooded" Palawa, a woman called Trugernanner (often rendered as Truganini), died in 1876. However, many people of Palawa descent remain and some aspects of traditional Palawa culture have survived among them.[PARAGRAPH:2]Almost all of the Indigenous Tasmanian languages have been lost. Currently there are some efforts to reconstruct one of the languages from the available wordlists and to revive the aboriginal culture from aspects maintained in some families who can trace their ascendancy from aboriginal people. Some members of the modern-day descendant community who claim ancestry to Tasmanian Aborigines are the result of the pre-colonisation Aboriginal population having been heavily intermixed with later-arriving European settler communities (particularly those originating from the British Isles).[PARAGRAPH:3]People are thought to have first crossed into Tasmania approximately 40,000 years ago via a land bridge between the island and the rest of mainland Australia during an ice age. When the sea levels rose flooding the Bassian Plain, the people were left isolated for approximately 10,000 years until European explorations occurred during the late eighteenth and early 19th century.[PARAGRAPH:2]In the Warreen Cave in the Maxwell River valley of the south-west archaeologists have recently excavated materials proving Aboriginal occupation from as early as 35,000BP which proves that the indigenous Tasmanians were the most southerly population in the world during the pleistocene era.[PARAGRAPH:2]After the sea rose to create Bass Strait the two land masses of the Australian mainland and the island of Tasmania became separated, and the Aboriginals that had migrated from mainland Australia became cut off from their cousins on the mainland. Because neither side had ocean sailing technology the two groups were unable to maintain contact with each other.[PARAGRAPH:2]It had been a long held view that unlike other populations around the world the small population of Tasmania wasn't able to share any of the new technological advances being made by mainland groups, thus making Tasmanian Aboriginals the simplest people on Earth. It had also been thought that like the mainland Aborigines, they did have stone age technology but because of the ocean divide they didn't share any of the mainland Aboriginal advances like: barbed spears, bone tools of any kind, boomerangs, hooks, sewing, and the ability to start a fire.[PARAGRAPH:2]However recent archaeological evidence has started to challenge these views. Very little is known about the nature of social, cultural, or territorial history of the Tasmanian Aborigines, but archaeological research has provided ethnographic evidence that debunks many long held myths about Tasmanian Aborigines. Although an explanation has not been found, it has been determined that approximately 4,000 years ago, the Tasmanian Aborigines largely dropped seafood from their diet, and began to eat more land mammals such as possums, kangaroos, and wallabies. They also switched from worked bone tools to sharpened stone tools. It is now believed that they also constructed basic wooden shelters and small domed 'huts' to protect themselves during chilly winter months, although it seems they preferred to live in cave dwellings.[PARAGRAPH:2]It had also been a long held view that the Tasmanian Aborigines had lost the ability to create fire, however recently found evidence not only debunks this belief[not in citation given], but suggests that like their mainland cousins, the Tasmanian Aborigines used fire to clear land and herd animals to aid in hunting practices. It may now seem as though they were better seafarers than previously thought, and were able to construct canoes which were sturdy enough to enable them to navigate to off-lying islands and exploit the seal colonies of the south and west coasts[PARAGRAPH:2]It is believed that prior to European arrival in Tasmania, the Aboriginal people of Tasmania were divided into nine main tribes with a combined population of between 4,000 to 10,000 people. Each tribe consisted of groups of between six and fifteen 'bands' of forty to fifty people. Although they seemed to remain loosely within regions of the island, the Tasmanian aborigines were a primarily nomadic people who lived in adjoining territory, moving from area to area based on seasonal changes in food supplies such as seafood, land mammals and native vegetables and berries. The different tribes shared similar languages and culture. They socialized, intermarried and fought 'wars' against other tribes.[PARAGRAPH:3]Between 1803 and 1823, there were two phases of conflict between the Aborigines and the British colonists. The first took place between 1803 and 1808 over the need for common food sources such as kangaroos, and the second between 1808 and 1823, when the small number of white females among the farmers, sealers and whalers, led to the abduction of Aboriginal women as sexual partners and Aboriginal children as labourers.[PARAGRAPH:2]These practices also increased conflict over women among Aboriginal tribes. This in turn led to a decline in the Aboriginal population. European disease, however, does not appear to have become a serious factor until after 1829.[PARAGRAPH:2]Rapid pastoral expansion and an increase in the colony's population triggered Aboriginal resistance from 1824 onwards. Whereas settlers and stock keepers had previously provided rations to the Aborigines during their seasonal movements across the settled districts, and recognised this practice as some form of payment for trespass, the new settlers and stock keepers were unwilling to maintain these arrangements.[PARAGRAPH:2]So the Aborigines began to raid settlers' huts for food. This resistance first took shape in 1824 when it has been estimated by Lyndall Ryan that 1000 Aborigines remained in the settled districts.[PARAGRAPH:2]Between 1826 and 1831 a pattern of guerrilla warfare by the Aborigines was identified by the colonists, some of whom acknowledged the Aborigines as fighting for their country. The colonial government responded with a series of measures to limit the conflict, culminating in the declaration of martial law in 1828.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Black War of 1828-32 and the Black Line of 1830 were turning points in the relationship with European settlers. Even though the tribes managed to avoid capture during these events, they were shaken by the size of the campaigns against them.[PARAGRAPH:2]George Augustus Robinson, a Christian missionary, befriended Truganini, learned some of the local language and in 1833 managed to persuade the remaining "full-blooded" people to move to a new settlement on Flinders Island, where he promised a modern and comfortable environment, and that they would be relocated to the Tasmanian mainland as soon as possible.[PARAGRAPH:2]Once on Flinders Island, they were left to their own devices. Of the 300 who arrived with Robinson, tragically 250 died in the following 14 years in poor conditions.[PARAGRAPH:2]In 1847, the 47 survivors were transferred to their final settlement at Oyster Cove, where — no longer perceived as a threat — they were often dressed up and paraded on official engagements. In 1859 their numbers were estimated at around a dozen; the last survivor died in 1876.[PARAGRAPH:2]The remains of the Oyster Cove people were treated with disrespect during the 1860s, with many museums claiming body parts for their collections, even though one of the central traits of Aboriginal belief is that a soul can only be at rest when laid in its homeland. In one case, the Royal Society of Tasmania received permission to exhume the body of Truganini in 1878 on condition that it was "decently deposited in a secure resting place accessible by special permission to scientific men for scientific purposes." Her skeleton was on display in the Tasmanian Museum until 1947.[PARAGRAPH:2]Other cases included the removal of the skull and scrotum — for a tobacco pouch — of William Lanne, known as King Billy, on his death in 1869.[PARAGRAPH:2]Body parts and ornaments are still being returned from collections today, with the Royal College of Surgeons of England returning samples of Truganini's skin and hair (in 2002).[PARAGRAPH:2]During the 20th century, the absence of "full blood" Palawa and a general unawareness of the surviving populations, mean that many non-Palawa assumed they were extinct, after the death of Truganini in 1876. Since the mid 1970s Tasmanian Aboriginal activists such as Michael Mansell have sought to broaden awareness and identification with Aboriginal descent.[PARAGRAPH:2]There is a dispute within the Tasmanian Aboriginal community over what constitutes Aboriginality. A group that identifies itself as the Lia-Pootah claim to be descendants of Tasmanian Aboriginal women, many of whom had been abducted and had children with European sealers that worked in the Bass Strait in the nineteenth century. The Lia Pootah feel that the Tasmanian Aboriginal Centre represent the Palawa politically but not the Lia Pootah.[PARAGRAPH:2]More recently there have been initiatives to introduce DNA testing to establish family history in descendant subgroups. This has drawn an angry reaction from some quarters, as some have claimed spiritual connection with aboriginality distinct from, but not as important as the existence of a genetic link.[PARAGRAPH:2]The Tasmanian Palawa Aboriginal community is also making an effort to reconstruct and reintroduce a Tasmanian language, called palawa kani out of the various records on Tasmanian languages. Other Tasmanian aboriginal communities use words from traditional Tasmanian languages, according to the language area they were born or live in.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_LEADER_VICTORIA_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Victoria [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]British Queen [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lived: [\BOLD] 1819 - 1901[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Background:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Victoria served as English monarch for 64 years - the longest reign in English history. She took the throne at 18, after the death of her uncle, King William IV. At 20 she married Prince Albert, to whom she bore nine children. The couple was very much in love and co-ruled for twenty years. She and Albert were quite interested in science, and in 1851 they inspired the hugely successful Great Exhibition in the Crystal Palace, the proceeds going to establish a number of public museums, including the Albert and Victoria museum; which remains one of the world's finest museums even today. [PARAGRAPH:1]During the early years of her reign Victoria was a quite active monarch, and she won the hearts of her people with her modesty and practicality. It was during this period that she performed her greatest service to the British people: she oversaw the transition of the British throne to a constitutional monarchy. [PARAGRAPH:1]When Albert died in 1861, Victoria was devastated. She went into permanent mourning, retiring from the day-to-day rule of her country and secluding herself on the Isle of Wight, where she was increasingly involved in somewhat dubious spiritual exploration. Her self-pity was legendary - a remarkable change from her youthful modesty and enthusiasm. [PARAGRAPH:1]Victoria's isolation and indifference to the management of her country left room for extremely talented prime ministers, such as Gladstone and Disraeli, to guide Great Britain into a golden age of prosperity and expansion. During this period the Empire came to dominate half of the world's area and population - including India and much of the Orient, as well as large chunks of Africa, Asia, North America and a goodly portion of the Pacific islands. [PARAGRAPH:1]Victoria believed that Great Britain had a mandate from heaven to bring the ignorant peoples of the world beneath the protection of the British flag. She felt that she personally had a duty to these untutored people, to educate and clothe them, and most importantly, to bring them to the church. [PARAGRAPH:1]During her reign, Great Britain grew from a moderate European power into the second greatest empire the world has ever known (exceeded only by the Mongol empire of Genghis Khan), an Empire on which "the sun never set," far overshadowing Imperial Rome in size and might. The Diamond Jubilee, celebrating Victoria's 60th year as monarch, dwarfed in pomp and majesty anything that a puny Caesar could have ever mustered.</English>
		<French>[H1]Victoria [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Reine de Grande-Bretagne et d'Irlande[\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Dates :[\BOLD] 1819 - 1901[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biographie :[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Le r&#232;gne de Victoria a dur&#233; 64 ans, c'est le r&#232;gne le plus long de l'histoire britannique. Elle acc&#232;de au tr&#244;ne &#224; l'&#226;ge de 18 ans, apr&#232;s la mort de son oncle, le roi Guillaume IV. A 20 ans, elle &#233;pouse le prince Albert, &#224; qui elle donne neuf enfants. Le couple s'appr&#233;cie particuli&#232;rement et dirige conjointement le pays pendant vingt ans. Tout comme le prince Albert, elle s'int&#233;resse particuli&#232;rement &#224; la science et en 1851, ils encouragent l'Exposition universelle au Crystal Palace, immense succ&#232;s dont les recettes serviront &#224; cr&#233;er un certain nombre de mus&#233;es publics et notamment le Albert and Victoria Museum, qui reste, aujourd'hui encore, l'un des plus beaux mus&#233;es du monde. [PARAGRAPH:1]Durant les premi&#232;res ann&#233;es de son r&#232;gne, Victoria appara&#238;t comme un monarque relativement actif et gagne le coeur de son peuple gr&#226;ce &#224; sa modestie et son esprit pratique. C'est pendant cette p&#233;riode qu'elle rend son plus grand service &#224; la population britannique, en transformant le tr&#244;ne britannique en monarchie constitutionnelle. [PARAGRAPH:1]A la mort d'Albert en 1861, Victoria est an&#233;antie. Elle prend d&#233;finitivement le deuil, se retire de la gestion quotidienne de son pays et s'isole sur l'Ile de Wight o&#249; elle s'engage avec force dans une sorte d'exploration spirituelle inqui&#233;tante. Cet apitoiement sur son sort est l&#233;gendaire et contraste fortement avec la modestie et l'enthousiasme de sa jeunesse. [PARAGRAPH:1]L'isolement de Victoria et son indiff&#233;rence &#224; la gestion de son pays laissent la place &#224; des premiers ministres extr&#234;mement talentueux tels que Gladstone et Disraeli pour mener la Grande-Bretagne dans cet &#226;ge d'or de prosp&#233;rit&#233; et d'expansion. Pendant cette p&#233;riode, l'Empire domine la moiti&#233; des terres et de la population du monde, et notamment l'Inde et une grande partie de l'Orient, ainsi que de vastes territoires d'Afrique, d'Asie et d'Am&#233;rique du Nord ainsi que bon nombre des &#238;les du Pacifique. [PARAGRAPH:1]Victoria pense que la Grande-Bretagne est mandat&#233;e par le ciel pour placer les peuples ignorants du monde sous la protection du drapeau britannique. Elle estime qu'elle a personnellement une charge envers ces populations incultes qu'elle doit &#233;duquer, habiller et surtout mener &#224; l'&#233;glise. [PARAGRAPH:1]Pendant son r&#232;gne, la Grande-Bretagne passe du statut de puissance europ&#233;enne moyenne &#224; celui de second plus grand empire que le monde ait jamais connu (le premier &#233;tant celui de l'Empire mongol de Gengis Khan, l'empire sur lequel "le soleil ne se couche jamais"), surpassant largement la Rome imp&#233;riale, en taille et en puissance. Le caract&#232;re pompeux et majestueux du jubil&#233; de diamant c&#233;l&#233;brant les 60 ans de r&#232;gne de la reine Victoria &#233;clipse tout ce que le fr&#234;le C&#233;sar aurait pu organiser.</French>
		<German>[H1]Victoria [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Englische K&#246;nigin [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Lebte: [\BOLD] 1819-1901[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Hintergrund:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Aufgrund ihrer langen Regierungszeit (64 Jahre) ist Victoria Namensgeberin f&#252;r ein ganzes Zeitalter. Nach dem Tod ihres Onkels Williams IV. bestieg die damals 18-j&#228;hrige Victoria den englischen Thron. Jahre sp&#228;ter heiratete Victoria Prinz Albert, dem sie neun Kinder gebar. Die Ehe war eine Liebesheirat und sollte bis zum fr&#252;hen Tod Alberts halten. Das Paar interessierte sich sehr f&#252;r die Wissenschaft und gr&#252;ndete zahlreiche bedeutende Museen wie das "Albert and Victoria Museum". [PARAGRAPH:1]In den ersten Jahren ihrer Regentschaft war Victoria eine sehr aktive Herrscherin, die mit ihrer Bescheidenheit und Sachlichkeit rasch die Herzen ihrer Untertanen eroberte. Es ist also kein Zufall, dass auch die Einf&#252;hrung der konstitutionellen Monarchie in diese Phase ihrer Herrschaft fiel. [PARAGRAPH:1]Als Albert 1861 starb, begann f&#252;r Victoria eine unabl&#228;ssige Zeit der Trauer. Als Ausdruck ihrer Trauer und Wertsch&#228;tzung f&#252;r den Verstorbenen trug sie bis an ihr Lebensende nur noch Witwentracht. Sie zog sich zun&#228;chst v&#246;llig aus der &#214;ffentlichkeit zur&#252;ck und gab sich auf der Isle of Wight ihrem Selbstmitleid hin, das den einstigen Enthusiasmus der K&#246;nigin fast vollst&#228;ndig &#252;berlagerte.  [PARAGRAPH:1]Victorias Zur&#252;ckgezogenheit erm&#246;glichte Premierministern, wie Gladstone und Disraeli, den Ausbau des britischen Empires und den Aufbruch in ein goldenes Zeitalter des Wohlstands. Am H&#246;hepunkt seiner Macht kontrollierte das British Empire mit Indien und gro&#223;en Teilen Afrikas, Asiens und Nordamerikas, etwa 50%% der Landmasse und der Bev&#246;lkerung der Erde. [PARAGRAPH:1]Victoria glaubte an den g&#246;ttlichen Auftrag, die Ungl&#228;ubigen in aller Welt unter den Schutz der britischen Flagge zu stellen. Sie erachtete es als ihre pers&#246;nliche Pflicht, diese Menschen zu unterrichten und zu bekehren. [PARAGRAPH:1]Victoria machte aus Gro&#223;britannien das zweitgr&#246;&#223;te Imperium, das die Welt je gesehen hatte, ein Reich, "in dem die Sonne niemals untergeht". Nur das Mongolenreich Dschingis Khans hatte die Gr&#246;&#223;e des British Empire &#252;bertroffen. Nicht zuletzt deshalb &#252;bertrafen die Feierlichkeiten zum 60-j&#228;hrigen Kronjubil&#228;um der K&#246;nigin an Prunk alles bisher da gewesene.</German>
		<Italian>[H1]Vittoria [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Regina d'Inghilterra [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vissuta nel: [\BOLD] 1819 - 1901[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Storia:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Vittoria govern&#242; in Inghilterra per 64 anni, il regno pi&#249; lungo della storia inglese. Sal&#236; al trono all'et&#224; di 18 anni, dopo la morte di suo zio, re Guglielmo IV. A 20 anni spos&#242; il principe Alberto, da quale ebbe nove figli. I due furono una coppia felice e governarono insieme per vent'anni, dimostrando un grande interesse per la scienza: nel 1851, organizzarono una grande esibizione al Palazzo di Cristallo, ottenendo un successo inaspettato, e con i ricavi ottenuti fondarono numerosi musei pubblici, incluso il museo Alberto e Vittoria, anche ancora oggi &#232; uno dei pi&#249; famosi musei mondiali.[PARAGRAPH:1]Durante i suoi primi anni di regno, Vittoria fu una monarca molta attiva e conquist&#242; il cuore della popolazione con la sua modestia e il suo senso pratico. Fu proprio durante questo periodo che rese il pi&#249; grande favore al popolo Britannico: organizz&#242; il passaggio del potere dal trono inglese alla monarchia costituzionale.[PARAGRAPH:1]Con la morte di Alberto, nel 1861, Vittoria rest&#242; sconvolta: si chiuse in un continuo dolore, ritirandosi dal governo del paese e trasferendosi a vivere sull'Isola di Wight, dove inizi&#242; un'esplorazione spirituale abbastanza dubbia. La sua autocommiserazione divenne leggendaria... un cambiamento radicale rispetto alla modestia e all'entusiasmo della sua giovinezza.[PARAGRAPH:1]L'isolamento e l'indifferenza di Vittoria verso la gestione del paese lasci&#242; spazio a capaci primi ministri, come Gladstone e Disraeli, che condussero la Gran Bretagna verso un'era di prosperit&#224; ed espansione, nella quale l'impero arriv&#242; a dominare met&#224; del mondo e della popolazione conosciuti, inclusa l'India e gran parte dell'Oriente, nonch&#233; vaste aree dell'Africa, dell'Asia, del Nord America e buona parte delle isole del Pacifico.[PARAGRAPH:1]Vittoria riteneva che la Gran Bretagna fosse stata incaricata dal cielo di portare la protezione della bandiera britannica ai popoli ignoranti del mondo, di educarli, vestirli e, soprattutto, portar loro la parola della Chiesa.[PARAGRAPH:1]Durante il suo regno, la Gran Bretagna crebbe esponenzialmente, passando da media potenza europea e secondo grande impero mondiale (superato soltanto dall'Impero Mongolo di Genghis Khan, un impero nel quale "il sole non tramontava mai"), eclissando l'Impero Romano in dimensioni e potenza. L'anniversario del 60&#176; anno di governo di Vittoria fu talmente sfarzoso che in confronto le festivit&#224; indette da Cesare erano insignificanti.</Italian>
		<Spanish>[H1]Victoria [\H1][NEWLINE][BOLD]Reina brit&#225;nica [\BOLD][NEWLINE][BOLD]Vivi&#243;: [\BOLD] 1819 - 1901[NEWLINE][PARAGRAPH:2][BOLD]Biograf&#237;a:[\BOLD][NEWLINE][TAB]Victoria llev&#243; la corona de Inglaterra durante sesenta y cuatro a&#241;os: el reinado m&#225;s largo de la historia de este pa&#237;s. Subi&#243; al trono con 18 a&#241;os, a la muerte de su t&#237;o, Guillermo IV. A los 20 se cas&#243; con el pr&#237;ncipe Alberto, al que dar&#237;a nueve hijos. La pareja, que se profesaba gran amor, gobern&#243; conjuntamente durante veinte a&#241;os. Tanto Alberto como ella sent&#237;an gran inter&#233;s por las ciencias, y en 1851 inspiraron la brillante Exposici&#243;n Universal del Crystal Palace, como paso previo a la fundaci&#243;n de una serie de museos p&#250;blicos, entre ellos el Albert and Victoria, que hoy en d&#237;a sigue siendo uno de los m&#225;s importantes del mundo. [PARAGRAPH:1]Durante los primeros a&#241;os de su reinado, Victoria fue una reina bastante activa, que se gan&#243; el coraz&#243;n de su pueblo con su modestia y sentido pr&#225;ctico. Fue en este periodo cuando realiz&#243; su mayor contribuci&#243;n al pueblo brit&#225;nico: supervisar la transformaci&#243;n de la Corona Brit&#225;nica en una monarqu&#237;a constitucional. [PARAGRAPH:1]La muerte de Alberto en 1861 fue un terrible golpe para ella. Sumida en un luto permanente, abandon&#243; las tareas cotidianas del reinado y se recluy&#243; en la isla de Wight, donde fue sumergi&#233;ndose en el opaco mundo del espiritualismo. Su pesar se volvi&#243; legendario: un notable cambio frente a la modestia y el entusiasmo de su juventud. [PARAGRAPH:1]El aislamiento y la indiferencia de Victoria con respecto al gobierno de su reino dej&#243; espacio a algunos primeros ministros de extraordinario talento, como Gladstone y Disraeli, quienes guiaron a Gran Breta&#241;a a una edad dorada de prosperidad y expansi&#243;n, en la que el imperio llegar&#237;a a dominar la mitad del mundo y de su poblaci&#243;n, incluidos la India, gran parte de Oriente, grandes territorios en &#193;frica, Asia, Norteam&#233;rica y la mayor&#237;a de las islas del Pac&#237;fico. [PARAGRAPH:1]Victoria cre&#237;a que Gran Breta&#241;a ten&#237;a el deber divino de colocar a los salvajes del mundo bajo la protecci&#243;n de la bandera brit&#225;nica. Estaba convencida de que era su deber personal educar y vestir a estos pueblos incivilizados y, lo que es m&#225;s importante, llevarles la palabra de Dios. [PARAGRAPH:1]Durante su reinado, Gran Breta&#241;a pas&#243; de ser una potencia europea de moderado poder a convertirse en el segundo imperio m&#225;s grande de la historia del mundo (solo superado por el imperio mongol de Gengis Kan, un imperio en el que "el sol nunca se pone"), muy superior al Imperio Romano en dimensiones y poder. El Jubileo de Diamante, que conmemoraba sus sesenta a&#241;os como gobernante, habr&#237;a empeque&#241;ecido en pompa y majestad a la mayor de las celebraciones que hubiesen podido ofrecerse nunca a un simple C&#233;sar.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
	<TEXT>
		<Tag>TXT_KEY_VICTORY_VOTE_PEDIA</Tag>
		<English>[H1]Vote for Independence[\H1][NEWLINE]It is only in recent times that a nation has acheived independence from their motherland through the popular vote of the people, rather than through the bloodshed of a revolutionary war.[NEWLINE]The first such country to vote for its independence, was Australia. Between 1898 and 1900, referendums were held in each of the six Australian colonies with a vast majority of the people voting for the formation of an Australian nation.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]In the Australian Colonization mod, the vote for independence is represented by declaring independence while in good (friendly or pleased) relations with the Queen.</English>
		<French>Ce mod n'est pas conçu pour votre langue. Veuillez choisir l'anglais.</French>
		<German>Dieser Umb. ist nicht für Ihre Sprache bestimmt. Wählen Sie bitte Englisch.</German>
		<Italian>Questo MOD non è progettato per la vostra lingua. Scelga prego l'inglese.</Italian>
		<Spanish>Esta MOD no se diseña para su lengua. Elija por favor el inglés.</Spanish>
	</TEXT>
</Civ4GameText>
